Guide to the Technology and Society Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Yale Technology Project records, Accession 1985-A-066
  - Raytheon Study, Series IV
    - Raytheon Company Documents
      - Industrial Tube, Mount Department (Box 39, Folder 25-36, Box 40)
    - Industrial Tube
      - Management Interviews (Box 40, Folder 37-47)
      - Preliminary Interviews, Mount Departnent (Box 40, Folder 48-50)
      - Original Interviews - operators, 1958 November-December (Box 40, Folder 51-53)
      - February Interviews - operators, 1959 February (Box 41, Box 40, Folder 54-55)
      - Mount Department Observations (Box 41, Folder 56-66)
      - Before and After Study, 1960 (Box 41, Folder 67-70)
      - Job Enlargement, 1960-1962 (Box 42, Box 41, Folder 71-78)
      - Build Up, 1961-1962 (Box 42, Folder 79-87)
      - Consolidation with Quincy, 1961-1962 (Box 42, Folder 88-91)
    - Raytheon Corporate Level
      - Summaries of management interviews (Box 42, Folder 92)
      - Management interviews, 1962 May 23-28 (Box 42, Folder 93)
      - Management interviews, 1962 May 29 - June 1 (Box 42, Folder 94)
      - Notes (Box 42, Folder 95)
      - Recommendations (Box 42, Folder 96)
    - Receiving Tube, 1961
      - Raytheon Company Documents (Box 43, Box 42, Folder 97-101)
      - Interviews (Box 43, Folder 102-106)
      - Engineering Case Study (Box 43, Folder 107-111)
      - Meetings and Notes (Box 43, Folder 112-113)
    - Power Tube, 1960-1961
      - Raytheon Company Documents (Box 43, Folder 114)
      - Management interviews, 1960 May - September (Box 43, Folder 115)
      - Management interviews, 1960 October - December (Box 43, Folder 116)
      - Foreman and supervisor interviews (Box 43, Folder 117)
      - Marketing organization interviews (Box 43, Folder 118-119)
      - Notes on meetings (Box 43, Folder 120)
      - Recommendations and notes (Box 43, Folder 121)
    - Semiconductor (Box 44, Box 43, Folder 122-131)
    - Consulting (Box 44, Folder 132-141)
    - Research Notes (Box 44, Folder 142-145)
    - Reports
      - Reports to Raytheon Company (Box 44, Folder 146-152, Box 45)
      - Reports on Mount Department (Box 45, Folder 153-161)
      - Report to National Institute of Health (Box 45, Folder 162-163)
      - Before and After Study (Box 45, Folder 164-167)
      - Repetitive Work (Box 45, Folder 168-171)
      - Job Enlargement - Theories on Job Involvement (Box 45, Folder 172)
      - Job Attitudes - "Patterns of Job Attitudes" (Box 45, Folder 173)
    - Duplicate Material (Box 47, Box 48, Box 46, Folder 1-173)
  - Photographs, 1863-1921, Series V
    The Ford Study was conducted by Charles R. Walker and Fred Richardson in the Spring of 1946. This was a period of great stress for the company, a fact which made the project interesting to Walker but also led the Ford management to discontinue the study in order to let the company "clean its own house." The study was wide-ranging, covering policy at the highest level, human relations among the executives, production supervision, and the assembly line itself. Both the corporate offices and the Rouge Plant (over 60,000 workers) in Michigan were studied.
    Reflecting the exploratory and preliminary character of the study, the material in the files is rather sketchy. The data about Ford is matched in quantity and interest by material concerning the ambitions, values and techniques of the researchers. The various sections of the study are about equal in interest and importance: none are particularly outstanding, and none should be ignored. No comprehensive organizational chart is available, but a list of the more important individuals involved in the study is attached.
    - Ford study (Box 49, Folder 1-18)
  - Kodak Study, Series VI
    The Kodak Study was conducted by Charles R. Halker and Robert H. Guest in 1949-1950, with the report being written in 1951. After some preliminary discussion (files 2-3), Kodak management and the researchers agreed upon a study of a program of conferences between workers and department heads that had been instituted in the Cine Kodak and Sheet Film division of the Kodak Park Works in Rochester, New York. Interviews were held at various levels of management and with some hourly employees. The report to Kodak is a simple review of the program, while the draft of an article on the program is quite theoretical (file 9, items 1-2). In addition to the organizational chart, notes on the organization of the departments studied are contained in file 8.
    - Kodak study (Box 50, Folder 1-9)
  - Dresser Study, Series VII
    The studies of the Dresser Industries, specifically the Dresser manufacturing Company at Bradford, Pennsylvania and the Roots-Connersville Blower Corporation at Connersville, Indiana, were consulting projects in emphasis, rather than research projects. The studies focused on specific problems of interest to management: human relations within the Bradford plant (report, File 17), the relationship between the individual companies and the parent corporation (File 18), and the special situation at Roots (internal tensions and poor relations with Dresser Industries; Files 19-23). Discussions with Dresser began in 1948, most of the work was done in 1949, and completed in 1950, while correspondence continued until 1957. The files are somewhat uneven in content. Some research material (interviews and observations) was not saved, particularly in the Roots-Connersville study. The final reports are quite comprehensive, and many of the company documents are significant.
    - Background (Box 51, Folder 1-23)
  - U. S. Steel Study, Series VIII
    The United States Steel Project consisted of two distinct studies: 1) the pending move of a steel plant from Ellwood City, Pa. and its affect on the plant, community and union, and 2) the semi-automation of the Lorain Works in Ohio and its social and psychological effect on the workers and work teams. The studies began in 1946 and were completed in 1952.
    Ellwood City
    On August 1, 1946, the National Tube Company, a division of USS, announced its plans to move its Ellwood City operations to Gary, Indiana, within 2 to 3 years. The Ellwood City works employed two-thirds of the city's industrial wage earners, and the announcement shocked the plant, union and community.
    The investigation of Ellwood City and the pending mill move was one of the most thorough surveys made by the Yale Technology Project. It involved an extensive examination of the city itself, of the Ellwood City Works, of the union and of top USS and National Tube management. Questions ranged from the most general to the most abstract (How to handle technological change in industrial society? What is the large corporation's responsibility and purpose?) to the small but important matter of "What effect will this have on any one particular worker and his family?" "Will a certain downtown business have to close due to the mill move?"
    The collected data included interviews (see files 21, 23, 65-90) with townspeople, with mill workers and mill families; with all levels of management, including top USS management; with union members and union leaders, including the International Representative.
    The interviews were supplemented by many documents (see files 18, 22, 47-64): plant, union, community and regional documents. Data from 611 spheres of community life (social, recreational, religious, educational, business) were collected. A thorough analysis of the local newspaper was done for one year.
    Many working papers and reports evolved from this study but most important of all, and the best introduction to the study, is the book Steeltown. It tells the story clearly and includes in its supplement some of the more important working reports.
    Lorain
    In January of 1949, USS opened the first continuous seamless pipe mill in the US, at Lorain, Ohio. This innovation constituted a long step toward the automatic factory. It improved product quality, increased production with fewer workers, improved working conditions and decreased the need for muscle while demanding greater mental attention. The purpose of the Lorain Project was to analyze the social and psychological effects of technological change on industrial workers and works groups.
    Interviews with management of all levels, Crew members and local union representatives were made (see files 28, 162-192). Three rounds of interviews were conducted with all members of the three hot mill crews in their homes. Company docments (see files 24, 152-160) were studied and many in-plant observations were made. As a preliminary investigation of 6 weeks, Frederick L.W. Richardson, Jr. made a study of the community entitled: "Community Problems and Group Conflicts" (see file 146).
    Several working papers evolved (see files 205-207) dealing with such topics as union-management relations, the immediate job, incentives, worker attitudes toward management, and the crew as a team. The best introduction, however, is the book Towards the Automatic Factory.
    - Elwood City (Box 53, Box 54, Box 52, Folder 1-139, Box 59, Box 56, Box 55, Box 58, Box 57)
    - Lorain (Box 63, Box 60, Box 62, Box 61, Box 59, Folder 140-222)
    - Duplicates (Box 65, Box 64, Folder 3-165)
  - IBM Study, Series IX
    The IBM project was simple in most respects and the research material may be readily studied. Besides the various items in the background files (files 01 - 05), the best introduction to the study is the group of reports written about it (file 67), particularly the monograoh by Charles R. Walker and F.L.W. Richardson, Jr., Human Relations in an Expanding Company.
    The Company Documents (file 06 - 16) contain some background material and much that is directly related to the study. Many of the research findings were formulated in charts and diagrams, contained in files 26 - 35 and 41 - 42. The interviews (files 17 - 24) and research notes (files 36 - 40) are obviously important. Little material is contained in the drafts or the articles and of the monograph (files 50 - 66) that was not in the published versions (file 67) but the specific reports written during the study (files 43 - 49) should be consulted. The contents of the binder notes (Section VI) were later typed and appear in the various files, and therefore need not be studied.
    The Tables of Contents accompanying this guide and placed in the respective files were prepared for files which seemed to require some explanation. Files which have no table are not necessarily unimportant.
    It was necessary to add several items after the study had been arranged; hence, files 4a, 4b, 4c, 4d; and 68a, 68b, 68c, 68d and 68e. Also, there are many notes of interest in file 40 "Miscellaneous Notes" due to the addition.
    How the IBM Study was conducted
    This study of the IBM plant in Endicott, New York, was begun in the spring of 1946 with the purpose of examining the organizational structure of a plant which experienced improved relations despite rapid expansion.
    For purposes of simplifcation, research was concentrated on those departments directly concerned with production: Machining, Assembly, Production Control and Inspection. The time periods of 1940 and 1947 were compared to describe certain organizational changes which nomally do not occur in an expanding company:
    reduction of levels in the supervisory structure
    reduction of number of employees and foreman
    job enlargement in the job content of many workers, some supervisors and all foremen
    Observation of plant operations (see III.B. and III.C.) and informal interviews with management (see III.A.) (most of the 1940 supervisors were still available) coupled with basic data for the two periods, supplied the bulk of information. There were few interviews with hourly employees.
    The plant's "social framework" was studied in terms of horizontal and vertical contacts - noting purpose, function, frequency, duration, who initiated and who responded. This framework was studied in conjunction with the technical enviroment (including plant layout and workflow).
    Workflow and job enlargement were important topics in the general study and were the subjects of separate reports (see V.E.).
    - IBM Study (Box 70, Box 69, Box 71, Box 68, Box 67, Box 66, Folder 1-75)
      - Binder Notes (Box 71)
      - Duplicates (Box 72, Folder 2-75)
  - General Electric Study
    The GE Project consisted of two similar though separate studies, one at the Schenectady Plant and the other at the Syracuse Plant (both in New York State). They both dealt with a change in the organizational structure of the plants. Schenectady management omitted the position of general foreman and wanted to take a look at what this meant and would mean in the future for the foreman's job. The Technical Products Department in Syracuse reordered its personnel structure, omitting the wiremen and installing a new group called the "Pre-production Unit." Both of the changes affected much more than simply the immediate positions and employees with new titles or new responsibilities.
    Schenectady
    In early 1958 GE and local plant management concluded that the foreman's job needed re-examination. The position of the general foreman had recently been omitted thus giving the foreman (and others) new responsibilities and new problems. Management had three aims:
    to broaden the foreman's responsibility and control over his production area
    to strengthen his relationship with his employees and
    to increase his stature within management and so increase the satisfaction he may derive from his position
    The Yale Researchers combined quantitative data derived from surveys and observations (see files 18, 19, 20, 44) with a case-study approach based upon interviews (see Section II.B.) of foremen, former general foremen, service managers, supervisors, specialists and technicians, the Superintendent, the Product Section Manager, the Union Relations Specialist the Employee Relations Manager and the Departmental General Manager, to determine the situation.
    The findings can be summarized as follows:
    The general foreman had perfomed many duties, in addition to the fondly designated ones, which were not appreciated before the change.
    After the change, the foreman had to deal directly with service groups. Manpower allocation was still presenting a problem when the study was being done.
    Three quarters of the foreman's time was spent on production matters.
    Only thirty-four minutes a day were spent on employee relations (not enough time).
    The foreman clearly had a new relationship to the Superintendent, his new boss, which presented some problems.
    The foreman's promotion opportunities changed.
    Communications down from management to foremen and workers were good, but upward conmunications were unsatisfactory.
    The foremen needed help in dealing with their new "Union Relations" responsibilities.
    The communications and services of the Employee Relations Section were considered inadequate.
    The foremen needed more technical assistance.
    The scope of the technical assistant's job needs clarification.
    Generally, the foremen found their new jobs to have too much, to be too insecure, not high paying enough and lacking in promotional opportunities. But they did like the challenge and frequently found it rewarding.
    Progress had been made toward the three goals although more work needed to be done on the last two.
    Syracuse
    The Syracuse plant manufactured electronics products - about one-fifth of which were built to customer specifications. There was a high ratio of engineers to operators because there was a constant need to innovate in order to remain competitive.
    "At the time of the study" wrote Jasinski and Guest in the Final Report, "the workflow on a new product, or a major revision...was similar to...other organizations. An idea was evaluated and the product designed in the engineering group. A prototype was constructed....Once the product was 'proved' and the necessary paper work completed, it was turned over as a whole to the manufacturing section. Up to this point, there had been very little exchange between engineering and manufacturing." This was the situation before the creation of the "Pre-production Unit." Management realized that time was being wasted and flexibility was lacking. In some way, engineering and manufacturing must be in closer communication.
    Management's goals were the following:
    To improve product design and thereby increase "manufacturability"; this would involve a closer matching of design with manufacturing capabilities and would permit standardization and simplification of production procedures.
    To allow for better advanced planning by improving the quantity and quality of information available to management to enable them to attain optimal use of available facilities and personnel.
    To reduce paper work.
    These goals would reduce product cycles, reduce in-process inventory and increase production effectiveness.
    In order to achieve these goals, management developed the "Pre-production Shop." The pre-production workers replaced the category of "wiremen." They worked in a pre-production area and all of them reported to the same supervisor. They assembled an entire unit and worked closely with the planner and production specialist and with the engineer and draftsman associated with the unit.
    The results of installing this Pre-production shop (in terms of the original goals concerning product cycle time, inventory and manufacturing efficiency) were very favorable. Development time was reduced even though the pre-production shop constituted an extra step in the procedure. Inventory fell 62 percent. And manufacturing performance rose 40 percent in four months. This greatly reduced costs.
    There were the following unanticipated goals as well:
    increased flexibility in production
    increased time available to the engineers for straight engineering
    high morale among the pre-production workers
    internal effectiveness of the pre-production shop
    About the Files
    Of the General GE Company Documents, only the Questionnaires and the Research Service Reports (Files 7 and 8) are of particular use in understanding the Schenectady study. The rest are about or by GE in general.
    As always, the Notes and Correspondence (I.C) are important.
    The Schenectady Study Files
    Of course, the Statement of the Problem and Plan of Research is vital to the Study (File 16). The proposal for a consulting relationship does not state the problem exactly; the study evolved into one of the Foreman's Job rather than the general implications of the omission of the level of the General Foreman.
    File 17 contains the Questionnaires which should be used in conjunction with the interview answers. Only interviews which did not follow the questionnaire or cover the same material have descriptions in the Tables of Contents.
    The Organization Charts and Personnel Data should be consulted and some of the Company Documents are important (Files 18, 19 and 20). The Correspondence (File 21) is as usual necessary to understanding the study.
    The Interviews (Section I I .B.) provide the basic data and should be reviewed carefully. The Interview Extracts (Files 27 through 43) are grouped by topic and question.
    The Final Report is located in File 52.
    The Syracuse Study Files
    The Statement of the Problem and the Plan of Research (File 53) should be reviewed carefully. The other Background Files are important, too. They contain the Questionnaire (File 55 ) the Organization Charts (File 56) and some very useful Notes (File 54).
    Files 57 and 58 of the Company Documents and some of the documents in File 60 are of particular use. The photographs however interesting, are not vital to the Study.
    The Correspondence should be reviewed (File 61).
    The Interviews are in Section III.D. and provide much of the basic data. The Interview Extracts are arranged according to question and topic.
    Besides the Interviews, Data and Notes on Personnel and Production provide the data for analysis (Files 77-79). They are of especial importance.
    The Final Report is located in File 83.
    - General Electric Study (Box 73, Folder 1-83, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76)
      - Duplicates (Box 76, Folder 2-79)
  - Merck Study, Series XI
    The Merck study was conducted by Charles R. Walker, Robert H. Guest and Arthur N. Turner in 1951 and 1952. The focus of the study at the Rahway, New Jersey plant was on management policy in advanced-technology industry. Reports were prepared on management organization (file 49), workers' attitudes (file 52-53) and supervisors' attitudes (file 54). Material on the nature and purposes of the research can be found in the background files (file 3, 5), in some preliminary observations (file 48) and in the final reports.
    Since the study was a consulting program as well as a research project, different sections of the Rahway plant, and different problems within the plant, were studied in response to management requests. These separate investigations were substantially alike, however, and the files have been organized to form one group. The organizational charts (file 8) may be consulted to determine the position of particular sections or individuals. These charts are also useful in reviewing the material concerned with problems in the organizational structure itself (file 49, 54, and many management interviews).
    Interviews with the hourly workers are presented here in two forms. Each interview is filed intact according to the workers' names in files 32-37, and answers to particular questions are grouped in files 38-46. These answers are tabulated in file 47 and the final reports are in file 52-53.
    One file deserves particular attention. File 49 contains drafts (no final copy exists) for a report on Morale and Labor Relations. This report covers management organization and labor relations comprehensively and it is also the most analytical report on Merck.
    - Merck Study (Box 77, Folder 1-54, Box 80, Box 81, Box 78, Box 79)
      - Duplicates (Box 81)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Study, Series XII
    The study of Jones and Laughlin spanned a three-year period: 1950 to 1953. It consisted of five distinct though similar parts:
    a study of training and labor relations at the Pittsburgh Works
    a training program written by Charles R. Walker entitled "Jones and Laughlin and the American Economy"
    an investigation into labor and human relations at the Monongahela Connecting Railroad (called Moncon), a subsidiary of J&L
    a study of the Otis Works (in Cleveland) with particular attention given to union-management relations and the problem of incentives
    the beginnings of a study at Aliquippa (it was cut short by a change of consulting policy by top J&L management)
    Final reports were written for the Pittsburgh study (see file 22), the Course on J&L and economics (see the entire division) and for the Moncon survey (see file 34). These make good introductions to the studies. For an introduction to the Otis study, see file 47 "Reports" which includes a 6-point action program by Charles R. Walker. This suggests the main subjects of investigation.
    The study of Aliquippa was cut short by J&L top management (see file 5, item 15). It is little more than a few notes, interviews and documents.
    - Jones and Laughlin Steel Study (Box 82, Folder 1-51, Box 85, Box 83, Box 84)
  - New York Trust Study, Series XIII